Francesco Scala

PHD STUDENT IN QUANTUM MACHINE LEARNING

Pavia. Italy

□ (+39) 3406416189 | ☐ francesco.scala01@ateneopv.it | ♠ Work page: fisica.unipv.it/personale/Persona.php?ID=591 | ♠ Personal page: fran-scala.github.io/ | ☑ fran-scala | ☐ fran-scala



Summary _

I'm a third-year PhD student in Quantum Machine Learning at University of Pavia, interested in classical and quantum machine learning and their applications in different fields. My course of study has focused on quantum computing, quantum information, state-of-the-art quantum technologies and machine learning. Thanks to my collegiate and representative of PhD students experience, I have gained various soft transversal skills. Apart from the academic side, I'm an outgoing and active person enjoying sports, gardening and traveling.

Work Experience _____

FULL-TIME

2021 - present

PhD in Quantum Machine Learning Università degli Studi di Pavia

Pavia – Italy

Quantum Computing, Quantum algorithms and Quantum Machine Learning for entanglement detection on state-of-the-art quantum hardware. My supervisor is Prof. Dario Gerace.

PART-TIME

Oct 2022-present Teaching assistant Università degli Studi di Pavia

Pavia - Italy

· Lectures on General Physics (1st year course) at the single cycle degree program in Chemistry and Pharmaceutical Technologies

Jul 2022- Dec 2022 Intern CINECA

Casalecchio di Reno (BO) - Italy

- Intern at Quantum Computing Lab at CINECA
- The project aim was the development of software tools for Variational hybrid Quantum Algorithms (VQAs) with a high level of parallelization allowing the exploitation of HPC infrastructures
- Programming language: Python

2018-2021

Part-time collaborator Università degli Studi di Pavia

Pavia - Italy

- Collaboration and assistance for the operation and custody of IT structures
- From 2020 and 2021, management of various engineering department websites (WordPress) and email addresses
- Support to the exam committee during online entry-tests at the University of Pavia

Education

2019 - 2021 Master degree in Physics of Quantum Technologies Università degli Studi di Pavia

Pavia – Italy

Graduation date: 23-09-2021

Thesis: "Witnessing Entanglement by Quantum Neural Networks"

2016 - 2019 Bachelor degree in Physics Università degli Studi di Pavia

Pavia – Italy

Graduation date: 24-09-2019

Thesis: "Machine learning techniques applied to the quantum many-body problem"

Contributions: conferences, schools _____

Nov 2023 Quantum Techniques in Machine Learning (QTML) 2023 CERN

Geneve-Switzerland

Short Talk: A general approach to Dropout in Quantum Neural Networks

Quantum Computing and Simulation Workshop ISTITUTO VENETO

Venezia-Italy

Poster: A general approach to Dropout in Quantum Neural Networks

Superconducting Qubits and Algorithms (SQA) Conference IQM QUANTUM COMPUTERS

Munich, Germany

Poster: Symmetrizing Quantum Machine Learning for Quantum Field Theory

Aug 2023

Jun 2023	International Conference on Optics of Excitons in Confined Systems Università del Sa Talk: Quantum computing platform with polariton integrated circuits	Lecce - Italy
Nov 2022	Quantum Techniques in Machine Learning (QTML) 2022 UNIVERSITY FEDERICO II Poster: Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing	Napoli - Italy
Ago - Sept 2022	VCQ & AppQlinfo SummerSchool 2022 UNIVERSITÄT WIEN Student Talk: Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing	Wien - Austria
Jul 2022	World Congress On Computational Intelligence 2022 IEEE Talk: Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing	Padova – Italy
Jun 2022	Quantum Computing Hard- and Software Summer School 2022 EPFL, ETH ZÜRICH Poster: Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing	Lausanne - Switzerland

Extracurricular Activities _____

Apr 2023 - present | Technical-scientific Committee Member BeQuantum

Online - Italy

- Production of technical posts
- · General posts review

May 2023 1st Place ETH QUANTUM HACKATHON 2023 - IQM CHALLENGE

Zurich - Switzerland

- Topic: Exploiting symmetries in Quantum Machine Learning
- Tasks: TicTacToe (given), Schwinger model (our proposal) [link]

Apr 2022 - Jul 2022 Mentee Quantum Open Source Foundation (QOSF)

Online

- Implementation of krylov module within tequila Python package [link]
- Mentor: Prof. Jakob Kottmann

2022 - 2023 Phd Student representative Università degli Studi di Pavia

Pavia - Italy

Jan 2022 2nd Place MIT IQuHACK 2022 - MICRSOFT/IONQ DIVISION

Online

- Topic: Quantum game with educational purposes
- Blackjack-inspired quantum game named QuHackJack [link]

Skills ____

- Programming skills: Python, C++(basic)
- Quantum programming skills: Pennylane, Qiskit, AWS Braket
- Mark-up: LETEX
- · Soft skills: predisposition to interpersonal relationships, teamwork, quick learner, proactive, time management

Languages

- Italian: Native
- English: Level C1
- French: Level A1

Publications

F. Scala F. Scala et al.		IJCNN 2022 Proceedings Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing	
J. Kottmann,	I	arXiv:2302.10660 Compact Effective Basis Generation: Insights from Interpretable Circuit Design	Preprint
F. Scala et al.		arXiv:2306.05072 Deterministic entangling gates with nonlinear quantum photonic interferometers	Preprint
F. Scala et al.		arXiv:2310.04120 A GENERAL APPROACH TO DROPOUT IN QUANTUM NEURAL NETWORKS	Preprint